Hey! Can you cover complex analysis? [Chatters
about people requesting complex analysis over the years]
Alright let’s do this. But why
should anybody care about complex analysis?
Well, just like any other field of maths,
it is beautiful, which is enough for pure
mathematicians, but for applied mathematicians,
physicists, engineers and the like, there
are quite surprisingly lots of profound applications.
It is very useful in solving differential
equations, because the real and imaginary
parts of a complex function satisfy a really
important differential equation. This equation
arises in many areas of physics, like electrostatics,
fluid dynamics, and heat conduction, but even
if you are not solving this particular equation,
for any other DEs, a common trick is to use
Fourier or Laplace transforms, which requires
tools in complex analysis.
If that’s not tantalising enough, it is
connected to some popular math topics like
the fundamental theorem of algebra, and the
Riemann hypothesis. Well, if even that is
not attractive enough, it allows you to show
off! No, seriously, how would you evaluate
this integral? Using partial fractions would
be a nightmare, but if we consider its complex
version, integrating on a complex plane, it
becomes massively easier. And actually, these
are only applications that hopefully *most*
of you would find interesting, but obviously
there are more! All I’m trying to say is
that complex analysis is very powerful!
And so I am going to make a video series about
complex analysis, and this is my plan. The
first one is this video, a preview of what’s
coming next. Then a crash course on complex
numbers, so that we can all be on the same
page, and then how to visualise complex functions,
and the messy stuff about complex functions.
And then a particular kind of complex function,
the Möbius map, and the slick way of visualising
it using the Riemann sphere. We can’t not
talk about complex differentiation, but it
turns out that if we want to visualise integration,
we also have to know a bit of vector calculus
first. But after all these, we are going to
see *some* of the applications mentioned,
possibly in several videos.
However, I want to emphasise that it isn’t
like this hasn’t been seen anywhere on YouTube.
Welch Labs made a series on complex numbers
and functions, Möbius transformations were
illustrated more than 10 years ago in this
video, Zach Star made a video on complex derivatives,
loads of people have covered vector calculus
before, and actually, this whole series will
be very much from this amazing book called
“Visual Complex Analysis” by Tristan Needham.
So think of this series as a more convenient
compilation and *my* take and animation on
this subject. However, a little note that
might be disappointing to the purists. This
video focuses much more on visual insights,
and the rigour is not prioritised in the arguments.
By all means, make the arguments in the videos
more rigorous! But in any case, I hope you
will enjoy the series ahead!
Thanks to these patrons, and as always, like
and subscribe with notifications on, comment
and share the video as well! See you next
time!